So, we've traditionally, you know, had all of our usage in DeFi coming from
crypto native assets, right? So I think currently we have just under 9 billion
in TVL, and I think that's really cool. But I think tokenized assets are going to
outscale crypto native by order of magnitude within the next 24 months.
And I think a personal goal for us right now is how quickly can we have that flip
happening chronicle, where, you know, we secure more in tokenized assets than we secure crypto
native assets.
All right, here we are with Nicholas Conkel, the founder of Chronicle Labs,
an Oracle provider for crypto and DeFi. Nick, it's agreed to have you on the defined podcast,
finally.
It's my pleasure. I'm so excited to be here.
And what a setting in Cannes for ETC. So really great to do this interview here.
Couldn't paint a prettier picture. Reality is a stranger to the fiction.
Yes, for sure. Okay, so I'd love to get started with the backstory of yourself and Chronicle
Labs. So your OG in crypto, you started out at Maker, built the first Oracle for the original
DeFi protocol. So can you, yeah, what kind of led you there and why start your own Oracle company?
Absolutely. I think, you know, MakerDAW was very early to having this vision of a DeFi ecosystem
that we thought might one day exist. And, you know, we thought a stablecoin would be very important
for that ecosystem. And that's what, you know, we set out to build. And in going through that
journey, it was like, Oh, well, we're missing Oracles. And we need some and they don't exist.
Right. So we had to build myself and Mariana Conti, we built the first Oracles on Ethereum.
But there were many other examples of this, like Texas did not exist. And so MakerDAW built the
first decentralized exchange on Ethereum. I realized that before Uniswap and Banker way before,
before Ether Delta, even. No, I did not know it was first called Simple Market.
Then it was called MKR market. And what later became renamed to Oasis. Oh, okay, I remember
Oasis for sure. Okay. Wow. I didn't know that. And why did you? So this is like a side track,
but like, why did you need the decks inside of MakerDAW? Well, because ICOs were not a thing
yet. And we needed funding. And so how were we going to sell our token if it wasn't listed on
a centralized exchange? So over a weekend, a gentleman by the name of Daniel Brockman,
he just whipped it together like in one weekend. He said, you know, that's, I don't think he
realized at the time, right, he created like a new primitive. So it was, it was a custom made
decks to sell Maker against ETH. It was, it could support any ERC 20 tokens.
And it was very primitive. So there was no order matching. So you could either create a buy order
or create a sell order. But someone else would have to click on that order to fill it. Oh, I see.
Okay. So if there was someone buying five MKR and another one buying four MKR,
if you were selling eight, you couldn't fill both of those at the same time. You had to fill five
of the first one. It was like kind of like a market place. It was very basic. But it was like,
it still appeared to be a completely decentralized marketplace. So at the time, like, yeah, this is
an example of how early Maker was and you guys were in DeFi. You had to like create your own
primitives to make things work. And so that's what happened when you were building an Oracle.
Can you go through the process of like, what was it, the pain point that you were
filling with that? So one of the problems that we saw was that Oracle's were incredibly
gas inefficient. And you might remember in the early years of Ethereum, gas price was a very big
problem. Yeah. Right. We had, you know, 500-way, 1000-way, I think during Black Thursday, we saw
7000-way, right? And this meant that running Oracle's was incredibly expensive. I believe in 2021,
Maker now spent $6 million on gas alone for operating Oracle's. And so, fortunately,
Maker now was generating a lot of money and could afford this, right? But this helped me identify
this problem that Oracle's had. And that was kind of the impetus for spinning out
Chronicle and really redesigning an Oracle from the ground up for efficiency. And, you know,
that's kind of what we did. I think we can do an Oracle update now in 52,000 gas.
And, you know, just for context, right, like the default Ethereum transaction cost is 21,000.
Right? So, it really like cut it to the limit, right? And that was kind of the first iteration
and kind of why we thought that this would be interesting as a product, right, to the bigger
market and not just to Maker now and its ecosystem. And so, what are some of the differences between
Chronicle Labs and some of the, you know, other big Oracle providers, a tain link with also now,
kind of up and coming? Absolutely. So, I think, you know, there's
clearly some differences in technology, but also, I think, in terms of, like, strategic focus.
So, starting on the technology side, what we do is use a signature scheme called short signatures.
And the only thing that's kind of important about them is that you can have this many-to-one
relationship of signers to signatures. So, you can have many validators collaborate to generate
a single signature. And this is in contrast to what most Oracle's use, which is a ECDSA signature,
which is one-to-one, right, one signer, one signature. And what this really enables us to do
is have a near unlimited amount of validators that can kind of contribute to consensus.
And that's really a kind of factor of, right, how secure are you, right, how distributed and
broad is your validator set without kind of having this gas inefficiency penalty of having to verify,
you know, 100 signatures, 200 signatures. So, I think on the, that's on the technology side,
that's like the core scalability improvement we've made. And so, we have, you know, many more
validators than most, and so we have some really interesting kind of like DeFi kind of flagship
projects that, or not even DeFi, but crypto, that run our validators, like Gitcoin, Infura,
MakerDAO, of course, but even, you know, some institutional exposure, like Bitcoin, Swiss,
for instance, who joined relatively recently. And there's many others.
So, what's the benefit for end users to having multiple signatures?
It's essentially a stronger security guarantee, right, that the Oracle cannot be manipulated.
The more broader of a validator set you have, right, the harder and harder it is for those
validators to collude in an attempt to manipulate the Oracle.
And what is the trade-off in doing that? Like, does it slow things down, for example?
Interesting, you should say that, right? There are some trade-offs because
a Schnorr signature, right, we said it's signed by many different validators, they have to sign
in sequence, right? So, validator number one, two, three, four, right, one after the other,
versus with ECVSA signatures, this can be done in parallel, right, because every validator is
generating their own. So, from a latency point of view, it is slightly slower.
Fortunately, though, I think given the even given the fastest block times that we see right now,
which is mega-eth at around 100 milliseconds, we can still generate Oracle updates significantly
faster than that. So, it is a trade-off, you're right, but it's currently not a bottleneck.
And so, we'll see how, if anyone else comes along, you know, that claims to have even faster block
times than mega-eth at 100 milliseconds. Okay, that's interesting. Okay, and then you said one
aspect was technical and then the other was strategic. Sure, so, I think we made a bet
very early on tokenized assets. I think tokenized assets are
really the next stage of DeFi and kind of a critical stepping stone to this
merging of traditional finance and decentralized finance. And, you know, one day, we will just
call it finance, right? And we really started on this journey earlier than most, probably because
Maker was the earliest adopter of tokenized assets. Maker had a really big problem where,
in the bull market, everybody wants leverage. And that means that Maker was making a lot of money,
you know, 300, 400 million dollars revenue annually. But then in the bear market,
nobody wants leverage. And so, you know, you would be making 50, 60 million a year.
And that kind of volatility in your revenue is not really great for sustainably running a business
and a team and investing in new products. And so, there was a real impetus to start allocating
and getting exposure to the traditional financial system in order to smooth out that revenue.
And so, you know, some of the earliest RWA projects were like centrifuge, right, who,
you know, even though now are starting to become a really big player right in 2017,
there was very little demand for this stuff. But Maker and centrifuge had been working together
since that time. And so, I really had like a first hand exposure to, okay, like, what are the problems
that AD5 protocol was having, trying to integrate a tokenized asset when, you know, it didn't quite
fit the mold of the native crypto assets that we were onboarding. And what kind of infrastructure
was required and what kind of data was required and what were like these extra risks that we
somehow needed to come up with technical solutions for. And so, I think that gave us a better
understanding than most of how oracles would change, how their role would change from wherein
DeFi, it's traditionally a price, right, a price to make sure the loan to values are reasonable,
a price to trigger liquidations. And now really encapsulating more of a broader data spectrum
to allow those DeFi protocols to manage their risk exposure to these tokenized assets in a smarter
and more automated way that mimics the ability that they have with crypto native assets.
So, what other type of data do you have to specialize in to really enable RWAs?
Absolutely. So, I think one of the most popular tokenized assets over the past 12 months has been
these tokenized money market funds or tokenized treasury bills. This doesn't tell us a surprise,
right, because the yields are very attractive and the risk is very low. And the issuers, right,
like BlackRock, securitized Biddle, right, like super state, like centrifuge, right, are fairly
credible. So, I think there was like a magic, magical kind of soup there. But to your question,
right, what kind of data is interesting? Let's use the tokenized money market funds as an example.
Each of these is composed of a portfolio of different short dated treasuries, right? And so,
even though the performance of the whole might be okay, it's the total portfolios
worth this much and it's generating this much yield, you can have maturity, distribution,
mismatches. So, what I mean by this is a treasury bill, right? It has a term and after that term,
it matures, right? And so, then the fund will need to go and reinvest that money into
newer issued treasury bills. When you're investing at scale, like Maker at Sky is, you know, in the
billions, liquidity becomes a huge concern, right? If that position needs to be unwound,
can you unwind a billion or can you unwind a billion over two days or over three days?
And so, the protocol needs to have the context of, well, what is, how much is maturing this month?
How much is maturing the next month? How much is maturing the following month? What type of
liquidity is there to sell these treasuries before maturity without having a significant
market impact, right? Where, you know, you would start taking on a certain amount of, right,
like losses, right, so to speak. So, these questions become really important when you're
operating on the scale of billions here. Now, treasuries, I think, are an interesting example
because they're the most liquid market in the world. I think where the whole problem kind of the
levels up is private credit and private credit is really where I believe we will see the most
growth. Well, it's the biggest market right now within our WAs already. Absolutely.
And it's also one of the hardest to deal with. I imagine a lot more opaque with liquid, obviously.
If you, for T-bills, right, there are hundreds of millions of people out there who are a potential
buyer off your T-bills. For private credit, there's maybe half a dozen, right? And so,
it is more difficult to model this already in a trad-fi kind of context and then
tokenizing this and kind of adds an extra layer of complexity there, right? You may have on-chain
liquidity and off-chain liquidity. And how do you reconcile those two? And is anyone more important?
So, it's a very interesting problem, but it's one that is an Oracle provider. We are tackling
now and it's more fun than I've had in years because it's a really interesting problem that's
not the cookie cutter DeFi formula off. Okay, here's a token. Let's get some price sources.
Here's the price, right? Okay, send it to the customer, right? This is like-
A lot more sophisticated. A lot more sophisticated and creative. And there's new challenges and
problems and it's so fun. It's interesting. I hadn't thought of kind of RWA's in that way,
and the fact that RWA's have been such a big trend in DeFi. And yeah, everyone is all for
bringing all assets on-chain and yeah, you have tea bills and private credit and then people
want to bring in everything from real estate and art. But yeah, when people say those things,
I don't think anyone is. The first thing that comes to mind is saying, okay, but how do we get
the data that's needed for this to work on-chain? So yeah, it's an interesting challenge
with all of these new markets coming onward. How do you foresee that evolving? So, tea bills
on private credit are like the big RWA focus right now. Are you prepared for like other markets
who come on-chain or are you just like focusing on these two to start? So clearly, private credit
and treasuries are the biggest in market size right now. So of course, we are very active in those
domains. But just yesterday, we saw Robinhood announce that there are going to be tokenizing
equities and especially tokenizing non-public equities like SpaceX, for instance, which
is a unique value proposition. So I think that's very interesting. I think in the commodities
side of things, so far it's been mostly gold. We had Tether, I believe last year or earlier this
year, launched a gold-backed tokenized asset. So I think that's incredibly interesting as well.
But yes, I do see the primary drivers of growth continuing to be private credit.
With treasuries increasing in size, but at a slower rate than what we've seen
due to the expectation of monetary policy becoming a bit looser in the coming
months, six to 12 months. Okay, it makes sense. But the next kind of
lower-hanging fruits you think will be equities and commodities. Yeah, absolutely.
Can you maybe take us back and describe why oracles are a different challenge for
on-chain market versus off-chain. How do off-chain markets handle their data and how is that
different from how that's handled in DeFi and crypto? So I think they're starting to be a
convergence. I think we in DeFi, we have quite a few people who have no traditional financial
experience, and yet we've independently come up with some of the same solutions as we've
quote-unquote "speedrun traditional finance" in just a few short years.
Right, the corollary to oracles in the traditional financial world are the data brokers. It's the
Bloomberg's and Reuters off the world. And it is almost like a regulatory requirement,
right, that you are getting data, right, that from a risk management point of view that you're
not just getting data from one source or from one broker that you have fallback data that you
rely on as well. And I think DeFi is kind of going through the same maturity cycle at the moment
where it started off that oracles were just getting data from on-chain and from centralized
exchanges. And now, right, we are starting to tap into those traditional markets as data sources,
just as I imagine and expect Bloomberg and Reuters are looking to tap into the on-chain
data sources to start offering that to their clients. And I think what will end up happening
is this convergence, right, where Bloomberg and Reuters will eventually offer oracle services as
well. It's my guess. And the oracle providers, like ourselves, like Chainlink will be directly
competing with them. Interesting. Why do you think your your edge would be in that case?
Right. So I think we're burning the candle from both sides, right? We certainly have
the crypto native experience, you know, not just from Chronicle, but even from the maker day. So
really building DeFi from the ground up. But I think also we are much more involved on
the tokenized asset side than necessarily they are at this point. And so I think that's our kind
of competitive advantage in that we can see opportunities and see what is potentially just
fluff and what is going to actually be like really, really big and make sure that we are
getting those opportunities, right? And we are embedding ourselves in that kind of fabric as
finance as a whole is going through this transformation. On their end, right, what benefits do they
have? I mean, their network, right? They already are working with all of the data providers like
the custodians, like the asset managers, right? And so that's probably our weakness, right? Because
we have to go and create those relationships, create those technical integrations. But it's fun,
right? Each of us has a superpower and we're charging in each other's direction.
Yeah. No, we'll be fun to watch how, you know, those two converge.
So can you walk me through your business model and whether related to that, whether there will be
a token involved at some point? So I think Oracle's actually have one of the more obvious
business models in crypto in that Oracle service that are necessary and the users of those
services, right, are paying us. So it's quite monetizable in that respect.
In particular, tokenized assets, I think, are one of the easiest to monetize as well,
because the asset issuer is usually kind of collecting some or fund managers, usually collecting
some management fee, right? And so, you know, our business model is, you know, we can cut off a
sliver of that management fee, right, for our services that enable this tokenization to be successful.
Okay. How do you determine what that fee is?
I mean, at the moment, it's kind of on a case-by-case basis, right? You know, we work with very many
different parties under different circumstances. But I do expect that there is some convergence
and on the tokenized asset side, I just expect it to essentially scale with the
size of the issuance, right? Okay. And regarding a potential native token, is that something you're
planning? It's not something that we're ruling out, but it's not something that we have immediate
plans for either. What's important to me is that if we were to make a token, that it makes sense.
I think we have enough tokens that don't necessarily have a purpose or like a real
utility. And I would not want to have Chronicle be one of those.
For sure. How can you optimize Chronicle to be the best suited for RWAs?
I think we're kind of already doing it in the sense that through our kind of
partnership with the sky ecosystem, including sky and growth, who are currently some of the
largest capital allocators into tokenized assets, we work incredibly closely with them. And so
those teams are at the forefront of most of the major tokenized asset issuance
in the space right now. And we try to partner with all of those. So the idea is that we will
be able to build up a pretty significant market share on top of what we already have and kind of
snowball from there. I think this is not very novel. I think Jane Link is very effectively
utilized the same strategy of converting a moat in DeFi into credibility with traditional
financial institutions. And we're kind of doing the same, but going through the asset
issuers instead for tokenized assets. Makes sense. And your relationship with maker and
sorry, sky now, that definitely kind of cements your place in that area. Absolutely, right? I mean
Chronicle is not a part of sky, right? We are independent. But there are enormous synergies
in what we kind of call the greater sky ecosystem. And, you know, in essence, there's almost like
a maker mafia, right? That kind of has left maker or stayed in that orbit and created new entities,
right? And which is how you got sky, which is sorry, which is how you got spark,
stake house, growth, M0, both of the co-founders. You had some of the fixed rates for the calls
like sense. So there's actually a very diverse group of ex maker people out there still innovating.
And, you know, we've all worked together for many years. And, you know, we trust each other.
So there's a lot of, there's a lot of value there. For sure. Now getting to what's next
for you? Like what are the big milestones that you're working towards? So we've traditionally,
you know, had all of our usage in DeFi coming from crypto native assets, right? So I think
currently we have just under 9 billion in TVL. And I think that's really cool. But I think
tokenized assets are going to out scale crypto native by order of magnitude within the next 24
months. And I think a personal goal for us right now is how quickly can we have that flip
happening in Chronicle, where, you know, we secure more in tokenized assets than we secure
crypto native assets. And I think we are well on our way there. Like the road is fairly clear,
but now it's time to execute. And I think over the next six, maybe 12 conservatively,
but six optimistically, where we're going to be able to get there to have a tokenized real world
asset set. Sorry. So then it's real world assets flip it. Exactly. Right. So 10 billion DeFi,
more than 10 billion token assets. That'll be an interesting metric to watch.
Related to that, actually, curious about your thoughts on the kind of the big criticism for
RWAs in DeFi, which is just like censorship or lack thereof of having RWAs in DeFi.
Absolutely. I mean, I think that's valid criticism. There is something to be said for keeping DeFi
in a purely decentralized context. I myself am a bit more of a pragmatist. I think that
in TreadFi, you already have a bunch of parties that don't trust each other necessarily. And
they've come up with appropriate risk controls, right, to manage exposure to protect themselves.
And so I think you can have completely decentralized chains with completely decentralized financial
primitives running on top of them that incorporate tokenized assets but keep the exposure
limited or at least diversified to such an extent, right, that even a complete failure in a particular
tokenized asset doesn't create any solvency issues for the financial credit engine that's
underlying it. And I do understand the criticism, right, why even integrate it at all.
But it's a question of scale. If DeFi is limited by what is the total market cap of BTC, ETH,
and Solana sum together, we're never going to get to the scale that we need to be and have the
impact on the world that we know we can have. And so it's a bit of a deal with the devil, yes.
But I think if done the right way, where people aren't too greenby and blinded by
adding another zero or two more zeros, right, if we're cognizant of the risk and responsible,
this middle path can actually be like the optimal path.
That makes sense. Then to wrap up, I'd love your long-term big vision for Chronicle. What would you
want Chronicle laughs to look like in 10 years or name your timeline?
My vision is that decentralized finance and traditional finance merge together. And we don't
even differentiate them anymore. It will just be called finance. My vision for Chronicle is that
Chronicle is just embedded in that financial fabric of the world. So it's not necessarily
that when you do a bank payment that you see all the stuff that goes on underneath,
right, you couldn't imagine that you're actually still using a mainframe from the 1970s,
right, written in Cobol. But you are. And I believe that decentralized rails are going
to replace all of that. And I think Chronicle is going to be kind of critical and central
infrastructure powering those rails. Awesome. That's a big ambitious vision. So very,
very happy to have, you know, heard it from you here on our podcast. So thanks so much for joining.
Thank you so much for having me. This has been great.